One of the interesting topics that was added when Spring Boot went to 3 was
the idea of introducing the native compiler to work with Graal virtual
machine images. There's a certain set of documentation here that's been included
in the Spring Boot documentation. So here I'm looking at the Spring Boot docs and
Section 15 is on what they called Graal VM native image support. And the idea is
that Graal is a special virtual machine that is made available by Oracle. And when you install it
as a Java virtual machine, it includes a tool called Native Image that will take your jar file,
your output executable, and compile it down to machine language for the platform you're on.
Now there's a certain weird feeling about that for Java people, because after all, we're supposed to
be right once run anywhere, right? Still, if you can create machine language for the platform you're
on, there can be significant performance improvements when you do that. So they have information here
about it and what it is especially good at is this idea that they're highlighting here called
function as a service platform. See, here's what Graal buys you is you get extremely fast startup
times with low memory. But the price you pay is that it takes time to build these images.
So every time you modify something you've got to rebuild, now your build time goes up considerably,
plus the executable you create is much larger than what you would normally deal with. So if you are
working with an application that really is function as a service, it's some stateless function you're
you're going to deploy in a cloud provider,
and it's going to sleep in between calls.
So startup time is everything.
So startup time is going to be hugely important
to an application like that,
then Graal's a great choice for that.
If you're building a standard RESTful web service
or an application that is just going to service web requests,
it doesn't really matter
if it takes a couple extra seconds to start up.
What matters there is that it responds
to requests very, very quickly.
So with this in mind,
I'm gonna go back to the application we did
in the first couple modules,
the one that accessed the Astro service
and had a little bit of persistence in it and everything.
And I'm gonna compile that for the Graal native machine.
Now, what they point out in the documentation here
is that you can do this with Maven or with Gradle.
Now, they do have to do all this extra static analysis
and they can't do anything dynamic.
They can't do any kind of reflection stuff,
no lazy class loading,
everything shipped in the executables
will be loaded in memory, right?
It's startup.
All this stuff is in here.
And they talk about doing what they call
ahead of time processing no less,
which always sounds funny to me,
but that's the basic idea.
So if I skip down a bit,
they have a trivial app in the documentation
that's just a RESTful web service, a RESTful controller
that returns the string hello world to a result mapping.
We're going to do a little bit better than that.
And you could work with build packs.
You could also work with, as they show here,
Maven plugin or Gradle, but those are working with Docker.
So this would assume that you had, say,
Docker desktop installed on your machine.
That's fine, and you can do that,
but what I decided to do instead
is download and install the Graal VM itself.
So with that in mind, if I go to my app here,
now the first change I had to make by the way
is in the build file, I had to add this line,
the Graal VM build tools native plugin
with the current version, whatever it is.
So I went to start.spring.io and I added that.
In fact, let me just show you here.
Here is start.spring.io.
There's the Graal VM native image support.
I added that to the project and when I hit explore,
that gave me the one line I needed to copy
and put into my file.
That's the only thing I needed to do.
That's one of the nice things about Spring with this
is that I don't have to do a bunch of setup.
And then when I opened up a console,
then I could run what they call
Gradle native compile step. Now I would run that now except then I'd have to
speed up the video because it takes somewhere between two and three minutes
to run through all that. So rather than run it again I'll just show you that it
basically put in my build directory under build there's a native folder and
and then a native compile folder.
And inside there, there's now an executable called demo,
right there.
So if I just give it the path to that,
build/native/native-compile-demo,
look at that.
It took approximately, well,
a 10th of a second to start up.
Now I've done it a couple of times,
so there may be some caching going on,
but basically by the time I hit enter, it was running.
That's the game.
Now what's the price you pay for this sort of thing?
If I look again at what we just saw,
well here I'll do it again.
The size of that executable is now 170 megs.
I mean it's got everything in it.
So it went up by a lot.
I remember I've got a couple of interfaces
and a couple of classes and one controller,
well and a rest controller as well.
It's just not very big as an application
yet it made 170 meg executable. But you saw all I had to do was hit enter. Here I'll do it again.
Bang! 0.093 seconds and it's running. So that's very attractive. It's very appealing to people
who are doing this function as a service idea. Now again you have to compile it for the right
virtual machine and you have to do it on each specific platform. But it's nice and the compilation
process is a little flaky. They're still working the bugs out. But this was the big addition in
Spring 3. I mean other than the upgrade to Java 17 and the use of the Java EE library with the
Jakarta packages and everything, the big addition was this support for the Graal virtual machine,
and you may enjoy using it. So have fun, good luck, you know, I hope it works out for you as well as
as it did for me.